Finding Aid for Middle English Dictionary records, 1925-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Non- MED MATERIALS
  - Manuscript Concordances and Collections by Charles Crawford
    - Other Volumes
      - [Charles Crawford], Miscellaneous Volume. Dated by Crawford after 31 October 1914 (see Part B, item 2). (Box 91)
        - Part A (in various hands):
          openings [unnumbered], 1-54: An alphabetical subject-index to Robert Allott's England's Parnassus (1600) (each subject divided into eight columns that cover a two-page opening (a facing verso and recto), six columns on the verso and two on the recto; beginning with the second verso of the index the openings are numbered from 1 to 54; the subject-index proper contains 1823 numbered items beginning with "Angels" and ending with "Youth" (both this and the next item are in Crawford's hand); the columns are headed: "No." (from 1 to 1823), "Page in Collier" [Collier's Reprints Vol. 3] (from 1 to 383), "Attributed to," "Found in," "References and Date," "Beginning of Quotation," "No. of lines adduced," and "Notes")
          openings 54-72: Additional subject-indexes in the same format (numbered 1824 to 2331 and covering pp. 383-582 in Collier), divided into sections: "The Division of the Day Naturall," "Poetical Descriptions," "Poetical Comparisons," and "Miscellanea," each section having a number of sub-divisions; with "End" on opening 72)
        - Part B (Box 91)
          (an unbound chunk of 42 unnumbered pages in three parts, all in Crawford's hand; probably part of the original volume)
          Index to Authors": 71 names, with references to where in the Parnassus they are found (34 pp.)
          Summary of Results [from the previous Index] 31/10/1914" (4 pp.:)
          English Names and Writings mentioned and quoted in Burton's Anat[omy] of Melancholy," alphabetically arranged but ending in early C (4 pp.:, some pages following May have been lost)
      - Charles Crawford, "The Paradise of Dainty Devices: A complete concordance of the poems in the editions of 1576, 1578, 1580, 1596 and 1600." This volume was compiled by Crawford in "March, 1916." (Box 91)
        Concordance proper, from A to Z, pp. 1-394
        "First lines of Poems, and the Signatures appended to them." (p. 397: Description of his procedure in what follows; pp. 398-489: On each two-page opening the numbered poem or poems are on the even-numbered page and the signatures of the five editions on the odd-numbered page; pp. 398-471: Poems of the 1576 edition (numbered 1-99); pp. 472-85: Poems in the 1580 edition not in the 1576 edition (numbered 100-17); pp. 486-89: Poems printed in the 1596 edition for the first time (numbered 118-24); pp. 488-89 bottom: An additional poem found only in the 1578 edition (numbered 125)
Related Materials
For the citation slips used in the printed MED (along with the supplementary slips), see the Bentley Library record group Middle English Dictionary citation slips (Call number 0183 Bimu 2).
For other University of Michigan holdings with administrative records related to the MED project, see College of Literature, Science and the Arts (University of Michigan) records (Call number 8779 Blmu C22 Bimu C22 2); Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies (University of Michigan) records (Call number 87198 Bimu C161 2); and especially Office of the Vice-President for Research (University of Michigan) records (call number 87258 Bimu B6 2 UBlmul B6).
For videos of the presentation of papers on the history of the MED and of the celebratory dinner and the festivities connected with it that took place in the afternoon and evening of May 9, 2001, during the Dictionary Society of North America Biennial Conference in Ann Arbor, see Office of the Vice-President for Research (University of Michigan) records, Box 170 (BMC 1575 and 1576).